Okay, so let me...
Ah, right, so all we've done is lost about 20 minutes getting set up and it still didn't
get set up quite right.
And I will try to figure out all the things that broke this time and do something different
next time for you.
But for right now, maybe we can proceed.
Okay, so the terminology first off, this is probably something that you know from a different
name.
Oh, that's...
Why, that's because...
Oh, you can't see the screen.
For me, you're a video and screener frozen.
Frozen?
Oh, okay, that's different from...
Oh, yes, sure enough.
It is frozen, so let me just try turning it off and on.
Off?
Oh.
Start.
Whoa.
It refuses.
Why...
Start stop camera.
Why will it not do that?
Actually, I don't think...
I don't think it'll kick you out at all.
All right, let's try it.
Here we go.
Because I'm actually speaking to you over the other computer anyway.
All right, now...
Oh, but now I can't...
It just cannot get a hold of it.
Oh, that's interesting.
Okay, I have to restart the browser altogether, I think.
I think this browser is dead.
All right, I'm leaving and coming back.
Bye.
Yep.
Yeah, actually, you probably hear...
Send to desktop.
You're muted.
I muted.
Oh, I muted.
Oh, all right.
All right.
We can hear you from the other computer.
Right.
And...
Oh.
And I was...
I was...
You can show this screen and then share the other audio.
Maybe that's what you want to do.
Yeah, I think that's what's going to happen.
Yeah.
In fact, just for a joke.
Just for a joke.
There.
Now you can...
Now you can just watch the back of my head.
We need...
All right.
All right, now.
And I'm going to allow this.
Okay.
Yay!
We got you.
But...
Okay.
I'm going to...
We got you.
But now...
I don't have...
What I don't have is...
Oh, yeah so I just don't have...
Oh, yeah so I didn't know...
But I just don't have the ability to do to individual from this computer.
Oh, you didn't?
On the computer.
All right.
Well this movie is going to be a mess to put together afterwards.
I guess that's just going to...
Well...
Done.
All right.
That's different.
My...
I can see the screen but I'm not able to see your video.
Yeah.
That's right.
I was coming from a different place from my screen.
So I actually would have a name on it.
I don't know the name of it.
I gave myself a name on it.
But if you see someone who's busy working on a different
computer, that's one of the cameras.
That's me.
Oh, if I have a camera.
Oh, there.
There we go.
Now that's completely worth asking you.
That's fine.
I'm actually physically in some room where there might actually
be the room at which I'm working.
So here's the thing about batch versus batch versus
active processing.
This is basically the history of the music.
So in 1957, I've actually done a lot of things.
I've been on an old line for computer and the basic deal was
what we call batch.
And batches make something like that.
You make a program.
It's a stack of cards.
It's just one, but I just want to put them.
Large number of them.
And someone else probably has to do it.
So they have a stack of cards, too.
And so on.
What I'm doing here is I'm moving down.
Time moving down.
OK.
Now you have a computer, which in the old days always was
identified with take machines.
And the deal is the computer in time takes a certain amount
of time to manage each one of these so-called jobs.
Each one of these things is called a job.
So job number one executes over some period of time.
And job number two, which might have arrived here,
is going to have to wait until job number one got done.
So here's job number two getting done.
And then sometimes you get situations
where the computer is actually idle.
Because you've actually done all the jobs that you've
been given.
And then someone gives you another job.
And then you get to working again on that one.
So this, so the, whatever you say, the flow of work,
or the flow of stuff to do happens like that.
And then outputs appear here.
And the outputs also, at least if you were working a bank,
the outputs also should up on a bunch of punched cards
at the end of the execution of each job.
So that's a job.
Now, music in was a thing like that in which the stack of cards
consisted of two things.
One was an orchestra, which actually the separation
into orchestra and score probably only
happened by about music three, as opposed to music one.
But at any rate, if you say music in,
then you're talking about the whole series of music programs
that Matthews was writing from, I think, 61 to about 64.
And then other people took on and kept on writing
until even present.
So at any rate, the thing that Max was able to do was,
OK, first off, the output of the computer
in the music one, I should write that as a thing.
So here's music one.
Actually, it was just called music, but we now call it music one.
And the deal there was, instead of writing
to a bunch of punched cards, you would actually
write to a tape.
And the tape was a nine-track digital tape.
And then you would walk or drive with your tape
that you'd gotten off the tape machine
to another thing, which was called a DAC.
And the DAC actually took tape as an input and did something
so that out came sound from a speaker.
Or actually out came an analog signal
that you could play to the speaker,
but more likely you would play into a tape recorder.
This was a real time process in the sense
that you would actually run the tape through this.
This was a different kind of tape reader from a computer
tape reader.
It actually read the contents of the tape at the sample rate
so that the DAC itself had no memory at all.
I just sat there and looked at ones and zeroes coming off
of magnetic tape and turned them into voltages
that you heard.
So this whole paradigm, well, there are two things going on here.
One is the batch paradigm.
And the other is the music in paradigm,
which sat on top of the batch paradigm.
So the thing about batchiness is that one thing
the computer can't do when you're, by the way,
you probably don't touch the computer in the classical situation.
You actually hand the box of cards off
to the computer operator or computer tech
who goes into the computer room and actually feeds them
into the card reader so the computer can run the program.
This is all done by hand.
So really there's an idle moment here while the person is putting
the new stack of cards in the tray so that the computer
can get started.
But the other thing that you can't do in a situation like this
is you can't have the computer stop and request more information.
So it's a commonplace of computer operation now
that you do something like go to a website
and then there's something like will you allow me
to use your camera question mark?
And then you say, oh, yes, OK, you can use my camera.
Or there any such thing where the computer is off doing
something but it wants some additional input of years
before it'll finish the job.
Like, oh, I know you want me to say,
but type in a nice file name for me to save to that kind of thing.
And that's that at its simplest is the thing
which is called interactivity, or at least has
been called interactivity as long as I know,
which is not necessarily that there
be any graphics or anything like that,
or even anything real time me in the modern sense
of the word real time or phrase real time.
But that the computer be allowed to stop
and ask the operator or person running the program
for additional information.
And this is important because, or it's a thing
because if you didn't have that, then you would have to put
in every bit of information that the computer could possibly
need in advance of knowing whether the computer needs it
or not.
Whereas when you're interactive, the computer only
has to ask you for the bits of data that are actually needed.
So that might be a small fraction of all the possible pieces
of information that you could possibly want.
So you can probably think of forms that you've all
filled out that have pages of stuff that actually
isn't relevant at all to the situation.
And no one will ever read these pages,
which you have to fill them out because the web form insists
on having all the fields filled in.
And interactivity is the idea of getting rid of that necessity
and having the computer only require input,
or have the computer go and request input
as opposed to simply run in so-called batch mode,
where input is all has to be present at the very beginning.
There's one other thing going on here.
In batch mode, which doesn't look the same in interactive mode,
which is that there's a queue that I haven't really shown
in this picture, but when you have more than one job waiting
to get executed by the computer, the jobs then form a queue.
And you can also say there's a queue at the output,
which is the output is sitting there in stacks of cards,
waiting for the person wanting the program run to come by
and pick the result up.
Both of those are.
Both of those are queues, except that, well,
both of those are queues and they have slightly different
characteristics because the job queue probably
is first and first out, whereas the queue where you just save
your outputs and boxes is a different kind of a thing,
more complicated.
So that's the quick interactivity versus batch distinction.
And the next distinction is various kinds of real timeliness,
so real time versus non-real time.
And here, once more, you need a timeline, which I will just
to be consistent with the last picture I'll draw it
as being vertical.
And then what you have is the following sort of thing.
So you have tasks, which I will just
show as a job, although it could be a job or something else.
And the task has a deadline, a time
at which we expect the task to have been completed.
And if you have a system that is set up in such a way
that each task that's given has associated with it
a deadline.
So even if you have more than one task,
each one has a deadline by which we
expect it to be fulfilled.
And in a situation like this, you might be running this first
task away.
So the computer might be running task 1 here,
until task 2 comes in and has an earlier deadline,
at which point suddenly we had better preempt task 1.
Let me draw this way.
So I'm going to put ellipsis there sort of.
And then here's task 2.
It finishes hopefully by its deadline,
after which we go back to working on task 1.
And then if everything is done correctly,
then task 1 gets done by its deadline,
and task 2 gets done by its deadline.
All right.
So this is an idea which is called hard real time.
And there are various ways of not doing this.
So for instance, if you are designing software for an airplane
where this thing might actually crash if the tasks don't
meet their deadlines, then you do everything
using a hard real time discipline.
And you actually try to prove that your processor
will do all the software jobs that are supposed to be done
each by their own deadline, no matter what the situation is,
that's to say no matter how the tasks arrive.
Of course, if the tasks are all required computation,
then you can't have a situation that's hard real time
if someone is allowed just to throw on as many tasks as they want.
That's you're just not going to be able to do that.
So instead, what you do in a hard real time contract
is you say, well, here are the tasks that can appear.
Here's the frequency with which they can appear.
Now can you prove that your scheduling algorithm
will get each task done by its deadline?
And there are various kinds of disciplines
that allow you to do this approvably.
And there are various other disciplines
like the ones for Max and PD, where you pretend to be doing that,
although occasionally you fail, because you don't actually
enforce that control over what tasks you're given.
So in Max or PD, you can always add more audio processing
than your computer can handle.
And then the thing will run late, even though it's attempting
to reach all of its deadlines, it fails.
And that's one version of what you might call soft real time.
There are many ways of softening the requirements
of hard real time.
But one of them is just say, well, we know what the deadlines are,
and we'll meet them if we can.
That's the Max PD way of doing it.
Other ways of doing it would be, yeah,
but the deadlines themselves automatically
adjust themselves according to the task load.
In other words, you have a, you get things done as quickly
as you can.
You make an honest attempt to get everything done in order
of whatever deadlines that tasks have.
But at the same time, you know that you might fail,
because someone might give you too many tasks.
And in that case, you would simply relax all of your deadlines.
And all this is, as opposed to non-real time,
where you simply don't worry about what time things come in.
And classical computer science has largely ignored classical
computer science.
I mean, the computer science of the 60s and 70s
when the discipline was getting its name didn't even
know about real time, because they were all
thinking really in terms of algorithms that
had inputs and outputs, which looked like batch jobs.
Which is much easier to theorize about than situations
where you have live inputs that you don't know how to,
well, that aren't completely specified in advance.
So that's something about what real time is about.
So then there's this, so the two terms that happen here,
one is deadline, deadlines.
And then another is latency.
So the idea of latency is this.
You might have a situation where every task has a deadline,
all right, but the deadline is actually
defined to be a fixed amount of time.
Let's do it vertically again.
But every task is required to be done
a fixed period of time after it is submitted.
So the deadline for each task is automatically
this latency, which I'll just call the lowercase L, later
in time than the task.
If indeed you have a situation where everything has
the same latency, then problems of real time scheduling
become easier than they were otherwise.
Because you never have to get into a situation like this one
with tasks one and two where a task comes in with a more
urgent deadline than the task that's currently running.
Because then what you have to do, if such a thing happens,
is you have to suspend the operation of task number one
while the more urgent task gets dealt with in, according
to its deadline, then you go back to it.
So this ability to suspend and resume execution.
This is, all right, term just jumped down.
I had it's not context switching, but it is.
The name will come back to me.
But this idea of being able to interrupt one task
while you take care of another task is something
you have to deal with in deadline schedules in general.
But if you have a latency-based system that
has a fixed latency, then you don't worry about that.
You simply know that nothing will ever come in with an earlier
deadline than the thing that you're currently working on
because it came in later.
And therefore you might not be able to get everything done.
But you can certainly always be doing the most urgent thing
at all times without ever having to suspend the operation
of one thing in order to interrupt it with another.
All right, yeah, sure.
And what that means, actually there are two things
that could mean.
One is you have some kind of control over how fast people
give you tasks.
Another is that sometimes you can redefine the situation
in such a way.
And this is actually something that people used to do
when they were talking about airplane design and whatnot.
They would think that the output that you have
is some number or some voltage.
And it's some function of the inputs.
So here are inputs.
And they change at times that we don't even know about.
But there's some function which doesn't have any memory,
which tries to see to it that this output
is this function of these inputs.
And then one of the inputs changes
and so then you have to recompute the function.
At this point, if the thing changes two or three times,
that's OK.
You only have to do the function the last time the thing's
changed in order to be as up to date as you can so that when
you add tasks, you don't necessarily actually add computation.
And then you can design systems like that, which actually
can run in hard real time no matter how fast the inputs
change because the requirement is only
that the output be consistent with what the inputs were
recently, where recently is some limit of time ago.
So that's a sort of a functional way
of thinking about hard real time scheduling, which
is different from the task-based one, where things are actually
in task.
You can't skip one task because another task came in
that superseded it.
Unfortunately, computer music doesn't work like this
because, for instance, an output might be a sinusoid.
And a sinusoid is not a function of its frequency.
The frequency is sitting there saying,
440 in the sinusoid is sinusoiding away.
And it's not a function of the input anymore.
And so this model of the output being
a function of the inputs is no longer valid.
So you have to actually go back to something more task-based.
OK.
So most of the situations in electronic music
look like this, look like tasks and latencies.
And this is a thing now that you can theorize about a little bit.
Now what I'm going to do is make two different kinds of time,
one of which is input time and one of which is output time.
So what's going on here is the following kind of thing.
Suppose you're picking up a bunch of details.
But suppose there are things that come in at random,
not random, but at unknowable, unpredictable moments of time.
So this would be like incoming MIDI messages.
So someone has a keyboard instrument.
They're pressing notes down on the keyboard.
And now what you have to do is you have to see to it
whatever you have to do about those things gets done.
And they get done by in this model, which is to say each one
has a particular latency by which its output should become
audible.
So then what you can do is you can mark the latency down
as an interval here.
And then you can draw two lines, one of which is out equals n.
By the way, that's the opposite way of from how you would
write this as a function you say n equals out.
Because out is on the horizontal axis.
And here is out equals n plus latency.
And now, so this is real.
Actually, what I can do here is I actually call this,
this is not really quite right, but I'll
call this real time as well as out time.
Because this is the time that things actually happen.
So what's going on?
What's going to happen now is that the CPU is going to get
busy at a moment in time when it can.
So the CPU is idle here.
This is all idle time.
And now at some point, the CPU will suddenly get a job to do
and it will start computing.
And so at this point, there will be logically, we are still
at this end time here.
Even though the real time is somewhat greater than that.
And at some point, we get our output ready, hopefully
before the latency hits.
And then once we get it done, then we stop computing
because we did it.
And now we're idle again until someone gives us another
thing to do.
And so now, what you can think of, well, OK, let me keep
drawing this thing.
So now, suppose this took a while.
I'm going to draw a bad situation.
So this took a while.
And then we got done with it.
Actually, the third request came in, but it actually
has a later deadline.
The second request is here, has a deadline here.
And maybe we even got that done in time.
But maybe someone gave us another input.
And that took some time to compute, too.
And oops, we are out of gas here.
And now we're late.
OK.
And then once we get done, we say, OK, we're not late anymore.
We're back up before our deadline so that if someone else
gives us something to do, maybe we can get it done in time again.
So if you look at this diagram, you can sort of see
the idea of accumulating lateness.
So the more stuff someone throws you to do,
the more late you're going to get until, well,
until at some point, if people are throwing stuff too fast
at you, then you get too late and you miss your deadline.
And then what?
Yeah.
And then I guess you're going to have some distance
that is just that after you get that one,
you're going to be relating it at some point.
You're going to run out of space.
That wasn't so far.
Oh, yeah, that would be a catastrophic failure then, right?
In other words, if, oh, right.
So implicit in that question is, yeah, there's a queue going
on because in fact, what you're going to do
is queue these inputs.
And that queue itself could fill depending
on how much memory you have.
Or actually, what could also happen
is if you're systematically pulling jobs
in faster than your CPU can handle,
your lateness will get later and later and later until,
at some point, you will just discover
that the audience has gone home
and you still haven't finished processing all of your
midi notes.
So there are various things that you can do here.
But at least while we're still on theory,
the correct thing to do is to increase the latency
so that no matter what the person at the MIDI keyboard does,
or whatever the person at the MIDI keyboard is going to do
is not going to push you past whatever latency you chose.
So in computer music, at least,
you actually choose the latency.
And you set it to be large enough
that you won't get these kinds of accidents,
but you set it to be no larger than you have to
because if you set it gratuitously large,
so at this point, this is an achievable latency.
And so is this, but if you ask for a latency
that's greater than the least achievable one
that you could have asked for, then you've got extra delay
in the system that you didn't have to have?
All right.
It's implicit in this, by the way,
that you want to have whatever the result of this is happen
at the desired time.
So a thing that is worse than delay,
if an instrument player is playing an instrument, say,
a thing that's worse than delay is uncertainty.
So you would rather have a known delay of, say,
10 milliseconds in an instrument,
then you would have a delay of five milliseconds,
but occasionally goes up to eight.
And this is just because if you did that,
then you would have three milliseconds worth of jitter
in the timing of the input.
And that would be a musical phrasing problem.
That could cause you to even, well,
that's not even an exaggeration of an pianist.
Things do happen at the level of a few milliseconds,
but you're not going to hear the sequence
being performed exactly as the person played it,
which is what you want.
So it's okay to hear it a little bit late
as long as you can actually make the timing be exactly
the timing that it went in,
plus whatever lateness you have.
Okay, so this gives you a way of thinking
about how you could schedule things in a hard reel,
but not guaranteed hard, hard reel way,
which is typically what you do with electronic music.
All right.
Then, and the good thing about computer music
is that if you miss one of these deadlines,
no one dies, so it's not like programming an airplane.
So you don't actually have to prove that no matter what
the human does, you won't do the wrong thing as a result.
Okay, so this is a picture that we might have to,
or we'll have to come back to it at some point
because when there are multiple processors flying around,
then the situation gets a little bit more complicated
and interesting, and there's still ways of thinking about it.
All right, I'm going to just check and make sure things
are still appearing to work, I guess.
Okay.
All right.
Now,
okay, so that's the thing about real time, non-real time,
and hard and soft real time if you are real time.
There's another thing that is kind of obvious,
but which is historically important, which is the hardware
and software distinction.
Oops.
And it was,
it's sort of been,
it's been gospel among computer scientists
that the correct way to do everything is in software.
That was true for many years,
that if you had to actually solve a problem in hardware,
you were in some way failing as a computer scientist
because your solution wasn't theorizable and correct.
Computer sciences, of course, now,
grown to understand that,
or to be able to deal with things that actually
have hardware implications,
but in the 60s and 70s,
the idea of computer science was the computer itself
was an idealized model, it wasn't a real computer,
and you never thought seriously about the amount of time
or about the temperature in the room
or about anything like that.
Whereas when people build hardware,
hardware could break and then not be replaceable.
Whereas software can't break, the computer can break,
but then you just take your stack of punched cars
to a different computer and run it there instead.
So software solutions have these advantages
of well, first off, and this is a thing I have to come back to.
The possibility of determinism.
That's to say, the possibility of having a situation
where if you give it a known set of inputs
that actually will create a known set of,
or a predictable set of outputs,
and if you run the thing twice with the same inputs,
you'll get the same thing every time.
Whereas hardware as thought of as not being deterministic
because well, for instance, it could be analog or digital,
that's a thing.
Especially if it's analog,
it never does quite exactly the same thing twice.
And yet, even when you're talking digital hardware,
when you, I have to talk about some actual hardware
and probably in a later class,
but when you start thinking about the actual way
that people design special purpose hardware
for doing digital signal processing,
such as, for instance, inside hearing aids now,
but in the 70s and 80s inside,
for refrigerator sized machines
that were specialized for doing audio DSP,
you have to actually think about the design of the hardware
as you're designing the software algorithms.
And that gives you an interesting layer of complexity
that you sort of have to think about a little bit.
Because in fact, there are still reasons
for moving into semi hardware
or even totally hardware solutions.
So there are trade-offs to consider there.
Determinism has, in real time programming,
determinism actually has two different meanings,
or there are two different senses
in which you could be deterministic or undeterministic.
One is just getting the right output or not,
and the other is getting the right output
on time or not, which is the harder soft
and real time distinction.
And one way of trying to write deterministic software
is to say we're gonna get it deterministically correct
and we are probably going to get it to you on time.
And that's in fact the way pure data manages to do it.
So it's hard to deterministic in terms of the result
of a computation and it's soft deterministic
in terms of getting it to you by the time you actually need it.
And I mentioned, I've already talked enough about latency,
so I'm gonna stop talking.
I'm gonna skip the latency issue
and just move on to the next thing.
Now there are sort of higher level software concerns.
One of which, let's see, I'm just gonna keep going
on the same page, I think.
One of which is archivedability.
Archivedability, this is a thing that computer musicians
sometimes care about and sometimes don't,
but composers really care about this,
which is the ability to write a piece of music
and have the piece of music actually be something
you can put in a library or in a music publisher's hand
and have them be able to present it to some performer
or performers later in time
so they can actually play the piece of music.
This was not a problem before music was ever written,
of course, so we can blame the monks
who started writing music down for even creating
this is a problem.
But now that a composition is a thing
which exists on paper as well as in the air as music,
it's a thing that you can ask a computer set up
to be able to participate in.
So you'd like to be able to make archivable electronic music.
And for many years, that took the form of magnetic tape.
So publishers would publish a piece of so-called electronic
music, but the music actually consisted of a tape
which you played over speakers at the concert
instead of anything live.
And this was often combined with live instruments
for a bunch of reasons.
The simplest being that live instruments
actually are capable of doing things
that you can't get on tape very well.
And another thing is that you can't really get the public
to come to a pure tape music concert.
You used to be able to back in 1948
when that was a novelty, people would actually go to watch
someone run a tape recorder in a room.
But even by the 70s, that was sort of like hard to argue.
So then what do you want to do if you want to actually
have the electronics be something that is more than just
a dead thing that's sitting on a piece of tape?
Well, then you have to do what everyone's been trying to do
which is make usable real-time systems for electronic music.
But those are, in fact, pieces of code that have to get run.
And then you have to worry about, well,
if I give someone this patch or worse yet,
if I give someone this piece of hardware
that I designed to do this bit of processing
be it analog or digital,
are they actually going to be able to do that
to play the music or not?
And the, let's see.
This has been a thing that a lot of people just torn their hair
out over.
So for instance, there are pieces by Morton Sabotnik
called the Ghost Box pieces where Morton Sabotnik's
assistant makes a thing which is actually inside a metal box.
This is a Sabotnik Ghost Box.
And you don't know what's in there,
but you can rent the Ghost Box from Sabotnik's publisher
and then you can play this piece for, say,
cello and ghost box.
And this actually happened at UCSD once.
The cellist actually got a hold of a ghost box
and played a cello and ghost box piece.
It can be done.
And that's okay as long as the Ghost Box is continuing to exist.
But music publishers are not going to be able to go in there
and repair the electronics when they start to get wonky.
And so then you need someone like Tom Erb to go collect
these old things and make it possible for musicians
to continue running these pieces that run on this old hardware.
Some of the Ghost Box, by the way,
had analog processing at it.
It wasn't digital at all.
Although there was digital control in it so that you could
sequence what the Ghost Box would do.
More recent, well, a bigger example is the great old
bit-slice architectures of the 1970s and 80s
about which I will talk a great deal more later
because they had a lot of interesting design issues.
But the Forex, which was the Eircom thing,
and then Stanford, actually, this was the end of a bunch
of, this was the end of the line of a bunch of series
of things starting with the 4A.
And one of them that I want to talk about is the 4C
because there was a, there actually is a published paper
about some software that ran on the 4C that was an early
attempt at doing interactive electronic music.
And then also at Stanford, there was a thing called
the Samson Box.
So usually it's called the Sam Box.
You can still see this thing.
It's still standing there at Stanford.
In fact, there's also a 4X sitting in the,
in Lovellette in Paris.
So the hardware actually still exists,
although it will not run the, who knows,
but something in there is broken in each one of these things
so that if you plug it in, maybe you'd see smoke
or maybe you would just not get any sound out,
which is the most likely thing.
So these are, these are both special purpose hardware
a little bit like, not exactly,
but a little bit like what is now our doinos.
In fact, I should write two things down.
There's our, no, just one.
Our doinos, maybe the most, the best known of these things,
but now, nowadays you can buy little processors on a card
that don't have any operating systems,
but which are in fact some kind of special purpose hardware.
In the case of the Arduino, it actually has a general
purpose processing unit,
but it doesn't run an operating system
and so it can't really be considered a full-fledged computer
or a whole computer.
It's just a thing that can do special purpose tasks.
So these are things and the,
the music that was written on all these objects has had,
well, our doinos are still around.
The music that's been written on Forex's and Samson boxes
has had to be translated in order to be realized a new.
And I actually am not up to date on whether anyone
is still able to run any of the Samson box programs,
but I can tell you that there are pieces
of the earcom that were realized on a Forex that are still played today.
And the, but it was done basically by understanding what the Forex was
and recoding the entire piece of music to run
on a more modern,
a piece of hard, more modern hardware and software.
So right now, as far as I know,
all of the music that was written on a Forex that's playable now
is played using either Macs or pure data.
And when I show you a little bit more about what the architecture,
Forex was like, you might understand
what might have been involved in getting that switch over.
Okay, so that's a little bit about the hardware software thing.
Why did people use funny hardware instead of just computers?
There were two reasons.
One was that until the late 90s,
until the mid to late 90s,
computer hardware did not come by default
with audio input and output.
So if, so analog to digital converters
and digital to analog converters of the sort that you would connect
onto a computer,
were usually add on devices that were,
that were rather exotic until they started being built into the,
into the standard computer hardware.
So in the days before about, I think before about 95,
but by 97, it was somewhat commonplace.
You could actually get a computer that would run at say 100 megahertz
and would have audio input and output built in.
I think primarily because of gamers,
gamers wanted to have audio on their computers.
And so if you could sell them a computer with built-in audio,
that would make the computer more valuable and you could charge more money.
Before you start,
you could be able to charge more money.
Before then, computers were really objects that people used
for banking or designing missile trajectories,
and so getting audio into and out of the computer
was not considered a priority at all.
And also it's difficult so people just did do it.
So at any rate, back in the Forex and Samsung Box days,
which would be the 1970s,
and even 80s for the Forex,
computers, you wouldn't be able to do what you did on a Forex,
on a computer simply because the computer didn't have audio
and put an output attached to it.
You had to drive over to someplace
that had a digital analog converter.
That's a slight exaggeration,
but people still were doing that in the 70s.
But there's another thing which is just the sheer number of computations
per second that was needed.
So if you look at the speeds of computers,
and I guess I'm just going to operate by memory here,
so I remember in 94,
the computer that I had on my desk ran at 25 megahertz.
So this is megahertz.
At 97, I had one that ran at about 100.
And then I forget,
but then it was roughly doubling every couple of years,
so let's just save by 99.
We were running at 200 and by 2001.
We might have been running at 400.
That might not be exactly right.
I remember these two figures pretty well.
Now, 25 megahertz roughly means,
although not really, roughly means that you can get somewhere
between a half of that and fully that number
of multiplications per second,
which is how you measured the speed of digital signal processing
back in the day.
So if you figure that sound goes at 44,000,
44 kilohertz,
well, 25 megahertz over 44 kilohertz is about 500,
I'm doing that too fast.
That means that you have about 500 multiplications
that you can do, I even,
some well, between that and a half that say,
multiplications that you can do per sample.
What that means is that by the time things hit about 25 megahertz,
you could do a kind of a simple patch.
As to say, you could get a few oscillators in.
An oscillator might cost about 10 of these things.
You might have 250 of them,
so you might be able to squeeze 25 oscillators
onto a 25 megahertz processor.
The Forex is,
the Forex came online,
depending on how you measure,
but they were touring,
they were beginning a tour with it seriously in 1982.
And the Forex was,
let's see, I need to try to remember this,
the Forex had a 120 nanosecond multiplication
that's to say,
it ran at six megahertz.
Yeah,
the multiplier ran at six megahertz.
And the thing itself had eight processors in it.
So between all of them,
you would get about 48 megahertz of multiplication.
So the Forex of 72,
just in terms of raw power,
got somewhere close to,
actually got much better than what you could do in 94.
Probably got pretty close to what you could do in 97
on a general purpose machine.
The reason it was able to do that was because
it was designed not to be a general purpose computer,
but designed to be a little multiplication machine.
So it did only those things that you absolutely had to do
to grind out audio samples and nothing else.
So you couldn't have files on it.
There was no,
there were no characters like you couldn't write the word
cat down on the thing.
There was no ASCII,
there was nothing like that.
There was just a bunch of number crunching stuff.
And it was the size of a full size refrigerator.
And that was possible to make in 82.
And that was possible to move on to general purpose hardware
somewhere around 97.
And actually, practically speaking,
it took about until 2000 before you could run 4x patches
on general purpose machines.
So they got an 18 year lead on everything
by building their own special purpose processor.
So that's,
that is, okay,
so in terms of archived ability,
they kind of,
they threw that away in a sense
because they just made something
that was only going to exist for the number of years
that they kept it running,
which was something like a decade.
It had a nice long life.
Hardware didn't change as fast in the 80s as it does now.
But at the end of that decade,
when the 4x started getting replaced by ISPWs,
which was another,
which was the next thing after the 4x that happened at EARCOM,
then everything that,
well, then there was a triage process
because pieces that had run on the 4x
if they were gauged,
judged to be important enough,
got moved over to the ISPW
and if they,
if they were just sort of orphaned,
then they just sort of died with the 4x.
Let's see,
side note,
I have kept a bunch of 4x microcode around
and I have a side project
to try to actually understand
how the microcode was interpreted by the 4x
in such a way as to be able to play
some of the old 4x pieces,
which would make it possible
to make period performances of
Fleet Manor music as it sounded back in 1987, say,
or maybe more interestingly to revive pieces of music
that exist on the 4x,
for which we might have the programs,
but for which we have no 4x to run it on.
And this is a thing,
so this is about archivability.
Sometimes a piece of hardware is important enough
that stuff that runs on it becomes archivable
because people make simulators for the thing.
This is true, for instance, of the Mac Plus,
you can run, or even the Commodore,
or MEGA and stuff like that.
You can run games that were written for those
extinct computers simply by emulating the computers
on a faster modern computer.
And that way you actually,
presumably, you get a way of running a thing
that is then permanent from then on out.
Actually, permanence depends on a couple,
or archivability depends on at least two things
that are important.
One is the hardware platform,
and that is not just the hardware that you need to
run the thing, but it's also the hardware
on which, or the storage medium on which you actually
stored all the stuff that you needed to be able to find.
And that's been, although it's stupid,
that's been a problem too.
So that's one thing that you need.
Another thing that you need is for the,
for software not to fall out of compatibility
with the past.
So a thing that happens constantly in the computer world
is operating systems get updated into new forms
that require that old programs be updated to.
And then if your piece of music relies on a program
that no longer runs on a modern operating system,
then you're kind of out of luck because then you will have
to find that old machine in order to be able to run your piece.
And then you could say, well, yeah,
I will just emulate a, let's say a 1995 vintage
Macintosh, which had a power PC processor and blah blah.
And you will probably find that that's not as easy to do
as it is to emulate, say, a 4x.
Because the 4x really is just a piece of hardware
for which we have all the software.
The, by 1995, or by 2005, especially,
the situation was complicated enough that, well,
to get a computer to run, you had to get the correct version
of the operating system and the correct version of all the software
and the correct version of the hardware all to work together.
And that, if you worry about things like copy protection
can become very hard to do.
It's almost impossible to revive a copy protected program
from another era.
And in fact, there are legal issues too.
When software goes out of print,
you can't just copy it legally.
You have to pirate it.
And you don't have anywhere to go
because the copyright owner might have fallen into bankruptcy.
You might not be able to contact them.
Or it might be copyrighted by a person who dies
and the executor doesn't know how to deal with it and all that kind of stuff.
Or you just might not ever be able to figure out who owns a thing.
So, practically speaking, stuff from the 80s
that ran on funky, doodle hardware is actually easier to archive
than stuff that was programmed in something, well,
let's just say some version of Macs from 1995 or 2000,
where you might have a serious difficult to get in that version
of Macs running again.
And in fact, this is partly an advertisement for open source software in general
because when software is open source, then theoretically,
at least you can go back and grab the version of software
that existed back in that time and run it on modern hardware.
Even down to the operating system.
Is that really true? It might be true. I'm not really sure if you can run 1995 vintage Linux
all that easily on a modern PC.
But you can at least have a hope of being able to do it.
You can probably run a virtual machine now and actually get, say,
95 vintage stuff to run.
If you can get access to all the software and if it ran on a decently published CPU architecture
and if there are no copyright issues or copy protection issues or whatnot.
And this is one of the main desiderata in the design of pure data,
in fact, is to make it possible to make archivalable electronic music pieces.
And it's doing pretty well in the sense that so far you can still run patches
that were designed in 1997, now, whatever that is, 25-ish, almost 25 years later.
And that's partly because pure data is open source and it's also partly because pure data
in its design avoids dependence on software packages of other sorts
that might have fallen to obsoleteness.
So in particular, the graphics interface and the audio interface and so on of PD
have been pretty resilient to the changes in programming methodology for graphics programs and for audio programs.
It's been partly luck and partly foresight.
Okay, so that's an issue.
The next thing, let's see, I'm running out of room, maybe I should just save this and move to a new window.
So this is...
Sure.
And is there a cure even for this?
What are the programming languages that forex and sandbox use?
Oh boy, no, I didn't.
Let's see.
The quick answer is the forex was written in a microcode...
Sorry, the forex was programmed in a microcode language called the forex patch language.
It didn't have any other name but that.
And if you're curious, I can show you some forex patch language maybe later because I'd have to go find it.
The Sampson box was programmed in a... there was a software system software environment for the Sampson box called Musebox.
And here, I'm operating by memory, I might be confusing things a little bit.
But Musebox was a thing which was written in the language sale.
So sale is a programming language in Musebox is the program that ran in it.
But Musebox itself functions sort of as a programming language because you would program the Sampson box in Musebox.
And sale is an acronym for the Stanford AI language.
Oh, do you not see my screen?
Yeah, I'm drawing... oh, you know what? Let's see.
No, why am I not showing my screen?
Okay, I have to do a thing which is...
Oh, drag. Now I have to...
Sorry, I had the screen on a different desktop and I noticed that if you can't like cancel, you have to go ahead and share something or else it will decide you didn't want to share anything ever.
Okay, now I'm going to try again.
Share that window and allow.
Probably what happened was when I saved the file.
I did a save as I think that is saved as.
Oh, you know what? I can do multi-page things here.
I'm going to do a little experiment here.
But for right now, I'm just going to...
I'm going to do a little experimenter to reshare.
I'm just going to try to remember to reshare every time I make a new window.
Okay, so now...
Okay, so next thing, plugability.
This is kind of stupid, but there's nothing you can say about plugability, but it's very stupid anyway.
So plugability just means you can say about plugability.
So plugability, so for instance, right now the way I'm doing this whole thing is I have...
So for example, Jack, right now the way I'm doing this whole thing is an audioIO-jack manager, which is taking my mic, which is a audioIO-compining-a-manager data.
So that is going to...
Combining audioIO-data.
By the way, this is going to...
That is going to...
...Pulse Audio.
Which is the thing which...
The browser knows about...
...which is the thing that what I'm trying to do is...
...make connections like this and also to the root screen recorder.
So what I'm trying to do is make connections like this and also to the root screen recorder.
And as you've probably seen, this isn't working.
So I have another computer on which I have...
So I have another computer on which I have another setup.
So right now what's happening is that the screen that you're seeing here is being recorded on one computer.
So plugability just refers to...
...having a few things to have a few things working on the black box.
have it having the ability to have it have inputs and outputs that box connect it in real time to other stuff
um inputs and outputs that connect this was sort of assumed this was just in a basic assumption of life
was sort of in the classical studio era which was part of the which was the analog days of the 1950s and 60s
which was part of the early days of analog days of the European 50s and 60s which were the early days of the 1950s
everything was just an analog a line-level analog connection because everything your studio just consists of a line-level analog
like for instance a tape recorder and so your studio just consisted of a bunch of that was important to have two or three tape recorder
and then you would have a nice oscillator that would be a box that was important and then if you wanted to make a sign and you would have an
actually physically wired your oscillator and then if you wanted to make a sign you take a quarter and run and
physically wired your oscillator and you had other stuff and then you could make different kinds of patches depending on the patch and you had other stuff and then you could make different kinds of patches
there's also getting rid of all this because it's but kind of there's also there's also there's also this thing else
there's also where for instance you're running able so able to make this software package where you get to where for instance you're running
able so able to attract you everything's going on and each track has a sequence of track you can have a sequence of
these tracks which has these things actually close running through you can't have a sequence you know your equalizer in the back
pressure and whatever running through and then you're listening to it equalizer in your press and so these these things are usually in the form of VST plugins
and this is this is a thing that did not well and this is this is a thing that this is a thing which has not really existed in a mature form
although it's a thing primitive forms for for many years before the VST
or something like that so for instance really by the time music now three came along there was a notion of unit generator by the time music three came along
there was the notion of unit generator this is a term that I think was invented by Max Matthews who this is the first music
term and I think so this is Max Matthews music three wrote the first music programs so this is so this is music and the idea to the unit generator was you would take the classical studio and the
class of the oscillators filter oscillators way VCA's I don't know how you filter VCA and then you would have an invulnerator VCA's I don't know how you make a VCA
this is stuff you would do in either classical studio or voltage control studio this is stuff you would do in either classical studio or voltage control studio
this is a thing which which max Matthews then this is the thing which which Matt Matthews then what he did was he started to use things as unit generators and started writing
what he did with bass language is what he would say instead of and started writing this thing like my knowledge is where you would say instead of VLT
so this thing might be OS and then you would say something like a one OS and then you would say something like a one OS and then a two and then would be filter maybe some frequency a one a two and then filter a one
and so a one in this case would be an audio signal which would be what was going down this one in this case would be an audio signal
this would be what was going down this wire so this would be a text language to describe a so this would be a direct detect graph which that explains a boxes and they're indirect
graph things of boxes and they're interconnections this has a lot of interesting ramifications when you do this digitally that did not exist
This has a lot of analog ramifications on it.
You do this digitally.
Looking a little bit more analog,
roughly at this, I should say the oscillator,
a little filter, hopefully at these things.
I should say this amount of the oscillator in the filter,
this belongs to the classical state.
This amount of patch, this belongs to the classical studio
era, whereas the idea of an envelope generator
with a voltage control.
Whereas the idea of a voltage control here,
an envelope generator with a voltage control,
this is a voltage control here,
or it's a control voltage, I should say.
Well, that makes this thing a voltage control module.
It's called the voltage control amplifier.
Well, that makes this thing a voltage control
module, just a voltage control amplifier.
This, this, it actually belongs to the voltage control.
And this is associated with the name some log.
This, I don't think, is really associated
with any particular name, past, past, this.
I don't think it's really associated with a shaft.
Because the classical studio basically
blew out of the shaft first part of the tape.
Because the classical or actually vinyl experimentation
that Chef Feref famously did in 1948,
and the French radio.
vinyl experimentation that's shaped Chef Feref famously
in 1948.
Oh, yeah.
So this is, this is really coming into its own 50s.
Oh, yes, so this is, this is really coming into its own
of the 50s.
And if you go looking at pictures of old stuff,
the classical studio looks a lot different from the old
central thing.
Because by the time a classical studio looks a lot different
from the old.
By the time this was going on, people
were actually building entire voltage control studios.
And so I want this to go on and it would be called
matchable synthesis.
I want to control studios inside one console.
And those are much more pictures on the studio.
See pictures of those a lot more often.
See pictures on this a lot more often.
So at any rate, this is a note.
This is a kind of plugability.
And so at any rate, this is interestingly enough,
plugability kind of plug means, means the plugs are
plugability wires into inlets and outboard jacks.
Plugged out, plugging wires and physical pieces of hardware.
Inlets and outboard jacks.
Here when you say plug in, you're actually
talking about plugging the whole VST thing.
When you say plug in your slot.
In other words, you should imagine taking something
like the filter and a slot.
Picking the filter up, you plug in into another larger
piece of hardware.
And picking the filter up and plugging into a large part.
But either those things are plug-in, some things are.
What that really means is that you're
really taking the same piece of code in some sense,
the same programming.
What that really means is that you're able to take
the same piece of software in some sense.
And the same programming uses it in configurations
that you control.
So the configuration of these boxes is
except that the person makes no music.
Whereas the design of the boxes was done by someone else.
Person making and music.
Whereas the design of the box is a bit of specialization
of a task specialization that is made at a very
deal of electronic music.
Specialization the idea that a task person can design a box.
And other person can just use the box as a tool.
Or some design without necessarily having.
And other person having had to learn that they would have
to do a little build the box without necessarily having
had to learn what they would have to do in our whole.
So plug-ability is another thing that you could say as well.
This is a thing, but this is actually
a particular kind of, another thing that you could say as well.
a particular kind of reusability.
And people in the software world use reusability a lot
as a term.
as a pluggability means something that is plugable
is reusable, but is reusability since being
able to plug it into the music like this, which
implies a sort of a flow of data between the objects
in a way that implies in a topology
that you've created that look at and understand.
A topologist who is connected to that.
So usability in general code is often
made reusable in ways that are not just
in general by connecting these two things together.
It's like a close that are not just
by connecting two things together.
There are all sorts of modes of abstraction,
which you can go into.
But some are going to be paradigm in a whole bunch
of abstraction and context.
And it can get a great deal more abstract,
herodime, and all of the business of just plugging stuff
together.
And it can get a great deal more abstract.
Just this business of just plugging stuff together
as if you were in a class.
The fact that the first off, music 3, the fact that this
is not real music 3 code.
This is just sort of what it looks like.
Music 3, this is not real music 3 code.
This is just a computer music 3, what are you saying?
Computer reification is a kind of a hudor of this kind
of a connection.
What are you saying?
Computer reification of this kind of a pre-existing
because of this kind of a connection.
But this comes into its own when voltage control
is a thing.
Because it's actually, when this comes into form,
it's going to be able to do this control stuff when you can
make it use things as controls.
It's going to be able to do this.
So in this case, we're making 440 hurdles
that we just gave this oscillator.
So in this case, this means 440 hurdles.
Or this could be in order to the audio
gave this oscillator.
And if it were in order to the audio signal,
this could be another oscillator.
It would be controlled directly by some other module
signal that we place to higher off the code.
that we place to higher off.
And this would then be what would class O
be called voltage control.
signal that some slippage of terminology
will watch out for.
Because this actually would be an audio signal, some slippage
of even though the free-sac should be an added to a VCO,
or EVCO, which is what I drew here, frequency that you
would use.
Those things are thought of as control signals
in the analog world here.
And those things are thought of as using three signals
in the analog world.
There's no distinction between here and control signal
on an audio signal.
These are three.
There's no distinction.
So everything is controlled in a non-sense voltage
controllable at that point.
And so everything is in some sense
voltage controlable.
One thing that I have, one thing I don't know.
And I think that I have gone back and forth about this.
But and I think people do actually know the answers to this.
And I think the simple gone back and forth about this.
Which of these two really actually have the answers?
So music three was about 19.
Which of these two really happened first?
So the music three was about 19.
Two.
The first modular mode hit the mark.
There's not first sure modular mode three hit the mark it.
Now, dead sure, but around it might be that mode
actually got some ideas from math.
Now, or it might be that math, he's got some ideas.
It might be that mode actually got some ideas from math.
It's not on the West Coast.
People are often in the West Coast.
And just he's got some.
So mode.
And that just happened.
It was out of the West Coast.
And he was often in the West Coast.
Or it could be that mode.
And Matthews were all looking back at the time.
Or it could be the mode and realizing that.
And Matthews were all looking back.
Where here you had a knob on NOSLE,
realizing that.
And that.
Where in here you had a knob that could be controlled
either by or voltage or by audio city.
So anyway, at some point or the development of a new way,
it's controlled modules by the mode
and the development of roughly at the same time
as controlled modules of software.
And this is roughly the same time as the music N
and the sound list.
This is a music 3, and the music N would be a generalization
of that.
This is a music 3, and the music N would be a-
People would be a-
People did call me, did regard music N.
But you can put this in quotes.
But this is a term that people use.
This is a subset of what's called
softwares synthesis.
This is a term that's used.
This is a subset of what's called softwares synthesis.
Another word for this stuff is music.
I think I'm just giving this term the wrong.
But music compiler, I think I'm just giving this term the wrong.
But this is a reference to the fact that when you-
This is a compiler compiler is a thing which takes-
When code, like C code, this one turns it into a binary,
which is a code, which is a thing that you could run,
which actually runs the binary, which is-
So here are music compilers, a thing where you write
out the instructions and runs the text.
So here are music compilers.
And the music compiler has us out with the binary,
which is text, will sound file.
which is the actual sound file.
And this is all done by batch processing.
Just to return back to-
Now, where do we go?
I think-
OK.
I'm going to just get us to the-
I'm going to just run quickly over the last couple of terms
and then-
Just get us to call a break.
And then-
So the way I'm going to run these classes is going to be-
So the A is going to be concepts.
So we're going to run these classes is going to be-
And B is going to-
A is going to be concept-
software or PD code.
So what I'm going to be trying to do is explain in the B's
the PD code that corresponds to the concept that I'm showing you today.
This will-
This will fail as I learned on a K outline because in fact,
the PD code isn't fair organized in a way that-
That you could-
PD code isn't organized-
Organize a class in-
In other words, it's not the case that the code starts in one place
and goes in a linear fashion until you get to the end.
And so it's going to be impossible to make the A's and the B's
actually line up terribly well.
And so it's going to be impossible-
I can get them to partially line up, which is what I've been trying to do now.
But-
I can get them to partially line up.
Next thing I have to say is this-
Right.
And-
Next thing I have to process is-
When you load those-
In-
Now for the folder content had a connection to the code.
Now for the ST  here it says-
Ah!
Okay so that was the tab form of that.
Ah, and-
Well okay.
Only one person could be running a job on the computer at the same time.
Only one person could be running a job on the computer.
These days we have what are called operating systems.
And operating systems can be thought of as a way to hold underneath.
And operating systems can be thought of as a way to draw underneath.
In such a way that you can have a whole bunch of programs running on this operating system.
And they can switch to have their own computer.
So the operating system is kind of a hack to take a computer and pretend it says many computers.
So the operating system is kind of a hack to draw.
And this is worthwhile because if the jobs are interactive in nature,
and you want to be able to take one job and have it wait for user input,
you want to be a while and not have the computer be idled,
which is the computer has other places of software that aren't waiting for the computer to be run in the meantime.
That's actually not a real-time paradigm.
That's called TimeShare.
And it's actually not a real-time paradigm.
And it's sometimes hard to share with real-time programs.
And sometimes hard to each reconcile that with real-time.
So when your program actually wants to talk to, say,
when your program actually wants to talk to on microphone,
the audio system,
the AC, the strong microphone,
which sends stuff into the computer's memory,
how it comes to the DAC, which sends stuff into the AC,
you just want it to be out of hardware,
how it comes to the DAC.
And the speaker actually uses the AC.
What really is happening is you're not,
and then the AC isn't talking to you.
the AC isn't talking to you.
This is what it would look like on the 4X.
But instead the AC is talking to the operating system,
which is what it looks like on the 4X.
But instead the AC is talking to you.
The operating system,
the operating system,
and the whole of other operating systems
have been created on the first bullet box.
And what we hear about it,
on PC,
we hear these pre-concentrationdated,
and your program will be in front of you.
see what the operating system actually adds latency. So the
other latency is added by the fact that there is storage here by the
latency in which it is like the fact there is the storage coming in and
queues samples that are needed to go out and I'll draw other
pictures later than show that in a great detail because it's worth knowing
much more about what that is. So operating systems are your friend because
it makes it possible to actually use the pauses with the current stacks of
cars around but they're also your enemy because they are between you and
the real world. But they're also your enemy because they are between you and
the real world. How you interface with the operating system is in other
words by what how you are facing the operating you as a program talk to the
operating system. By what means you as well as the operating system
interface or it's also perhaps a bunch of APIs that have the
operating system interface or also programming interfaces. And those are
things which you have to then deal with in order to figure out those are things
which you have to audio into out of your program and also what are
what are whatever other controls are displayed. And also what are what are
what are what are what are that's a thing that's that's the OS interface to worry
about. So that's a thing that's and I'm just writing that down because
every piece of at least every piece that isn't running on raw hardware
every piece of software that isn't running on raw hardware has to deal with
and know it's interface instead of dealing with the hard software that isn't
running on raw hardware. And finally there's the issue of graphical and text
environments which is the issue of whether you are coding something like this
which is again the issue or whether you are building something like this
which looks like a patch or you're in the way I've drawn it makes it look like
you'd much rather be doing music in because it's the way I've drawn it makes
it look like you're in fact doing music in a lot of ways that is a lot cleaner
than any any any graphical interface would be. In a lot of ways that is a lot
so it's worth thinking about the and the ramifications. We're thinking about
both negative and positive of graphical programming versus text program.
Both negative and positive of graphical programming versus text programming.
So to make a very simple example if you wanted to if you wanted to sound to do
it. So to make a very simple example if you wanted to that's much easier to
express graphically than it is to express textually. That's much easier to but
if you want to do this. But if you want to do this. Sorry that's much easier
described in text than it is in a picture. Sorry. Count to a hundred. That's
much easier. There's a picture for it. It's a thing that you can easily describe
in text. Whereas connect my oscillator to my speaker. Please describe in
text. Whereas that's the thing. I'll say that is much easier to describe
graphically than textually. That's the thing. Well, it's much easier. Maybe
maybe not because again you get quickly into these situations and and maybe
actually prefer to do that. Again you get quickly into these situations and and
maybe actually prefer to be doing that. On the other hand people think much more
readily in graphical terms than in textural terms. On the other hand they're
thinking about passion is thinking about processing signal flow. And so
frequently there's going to be some kind of a boundary between what aspect of
what you're doing is graphical and what's the basic which is a boundary between
and the management of that boundary design that is and the management of a
boundary thing that you have to get under control. You're thinking that you
have to a piece of music software. That's actually true of real time software
but it's true of music software in general. Actually we have really
a lot of graphical versus text slash procedural general. You really have to
describe things. Text slash procedural way of describing because procedures
are not well done in graphics. Okay because procedures are not well done. It's 80
minutes in even if we count the 20 five or so minutes that it's 80 minutes in
the audience. So I'm going to take a 15 minute break and we're just going at
16 o'clock or 15 o'clock and 4 o'clock PM. Maybe I will have 4 o'clock. Actually I'm
not going to try to touch anything. I'm just asking what it is. Maybe I will have
actually I'm not going to try to touch anything. I think that's okay. I had a
question. Yeah. I guess I was like trying to know your perspective on say you
took you managed to get a pv patch to become an executable. Then you go
around into the issue of eventually the CPU that's used to run that executable
might be changed. And then you're not going to find the hardware that actually runs
that executable. Then the problem of archived ability is seems like impossible.
Well there are a couple things like you can't predict happen in your favor.
What is a couple things compilers happen in your favor are usually designed in
particularity. So for instance if you write code that actually talks directly about
the registers that is so for instance if you write code that actually you will have
different registers. But if you just use variable names variables and load the
compiler allocate very few registers then you get a variable name because you just
compile the code for different processor and a story works registers then you get
away with it. Then where it gets trickier is actually the APIs and the operating
system interfaces. Then where do you have actually the API for the hardware
interface if you don't right because those things change more to the hardware
that the surface the code because those things change. So for the operating systems
for instance one thing that changed recently was I so for the operating
system six came so now change recently if you want to write network code you have
to be prepared six came out so now six now if you want to write network code you
have to be prepared for people to have I and that's a change in the operating
system that requires that you go in and edit that's the program change in the
operating system that requires you go in in fact PD is
going to get updated to network deal with IPv6 in fact PD is having
thank you to primarily I think deal with IPv6 which I think primarily I think
only thinking robot cowboy but I've forgotten Dan Dan Wilcox only thinking
cowboy so and then if you're quoting actual hardware like you know an
Arduino and then if you're quoting actual hardware like you know an Arduino
switch then on pin number three has a particular hardware interest that you have
to do to get the hardware address and that other break as soon as you try to
get to a different piece of hardware and that code will break as soon as you try to
move to a different piece of hardware right I mean I guess that at the end of
the day you do your best the only thing that could like really disrupt things
like quantum computing but on any other sort of you know level we're going to
still have these architectures that we have for there's a
Quarty is a Quarty effect that sets in all right well there's a Quarty of
course there probably a bit actually word is that's the Quarty but everyone's
stuck with Quarty you know Intel hardware Intel processors are I believe
pretty much stuck in Intel hardware Intel processor so you pretty much
still compatible all with that which is 1980s I think so so yeah things do
ossify in fact how things get how things get yeah things and do
addables in fact how things that things how things get usually that I owe
like for instance it's harder and harder to plug your MIDI keyboard into a
computer because it's hard hard hard meeting interfaith years
or he gets to computer because MIDI so real hard to the extent that you're
dealing with with with hardware so to the extent that you're the dodgy with
hardware operating systems are sort of a middle ground and then and then
it's easier to see could sort of deal with abstractions like numbers and
then your procedure for taking future proof with that's traction and so part of
the part of the strategy is to try or part of the a good strategy is to try to
part of it as much of your strategy is to try in that part of a good strategy
is to try to make world neutral zone that the zone of pure computation as you
can get it world neutral zone yeah I mean that's a lot more detailed
okay yeah I mean that's partial answer there's a lot yeah yeah it's a lot more
into it yeah it's hard problem yeah it is it will go later well I will spend a
few minutes trying to see what's wrong with my setup well I will spend a few
minutes trying to see what's wrong with my setup
first I'm taking a quick break